Guide to the Norman Foerster Papers, 1918-1940
Department of Special Collections
Norman Foerster Papers,
1918-1940
Special Collections M0173
Foerster, Norman, 1887-
3 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Restricted access: requires 24 hour paging period.
Provenance
Gift of Norman Foerster, 1967.
Biographical Note
FOERSTER, NORMAN, 1887-present
A.B. Harvard: 1910; A.M., Univ. of Wisconsin: 1912; Litt.D., U. of South: 1931.
University professor and instigator of New Humanist movement in American criticism. As its chief spokesman, he edited its manifesto Humanism and America (1930). Instructor in English, U. of Wis., 1911-14; assoc prof. English, U. of North Carolina, 1914-19, prof., 1919-30; dir. School of Letters and prof. English, U. of Ia., 1930-44; visiting prof. English, Duke University, 1948-9. Author of Outlines and Summaries, Sentences and Thinking, Nature in American Literature, American Criticism, The American Scholar, Towards Standards, The American State University, The Future of the Liberal College, The Humanities and the Common Man. Editor of Essays for College Men, Selected Literary Essays from James Russell Lowell, Chief American Prose Writers, American Ideals, English poetry of the 19th century, American Poetry and Prose, Humanism and America, and American Critical Essays.
Scope and Content
Letters and manuscripts, 1918-1940, pertaining to New Humanism movement of the 1920's. New Humanism is a philosophical and critical movement that flourished in the U.S. under the leadership of Irving Babbitt and Paul E. More, whose 1929-1930 articles and correspondence with Foerster comprise the bulk of the collection. Foerster and T.S. Eliot were members of the movement which stressed the human ethical elements of existence, as distinguished from the supernatural or animal elements. Collection includes prepublication drafts, clippings, research notes, and correspondence; a total of 1,000 items in 5 boxes.
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1. 1918, Sept. 2,G.R. Elliott to Ed. of Nation. Criticism of review of P.E. Morets Platonism., T.L.S. (open letter)
  - 2. 1918, Oct. 3,Karl Young to G. R. Elliot on curriculum for Ph.D., T.L.S.
  - 3. 1918, Nov. 8,William W. Lawrence to G.R. Elliott, curriculum for Ph.D., T.L.S.
  - 4. 1918, Nov. 11,Percy Boyuton to N. Foerster, on Ph.D. requirements., T.L.S.
  - 5. 1918, Nov. 20,Karl Young to N.F. on Ph.D. program., T.L.S.
  - 6. 1918, Nov. 26,W.G. Howard to N.F. on the Ph.D., T.L.S.
  - 7. 1918, Dec. 2,H.M. Jones to N.F. on the Ph.D., T.L.S.
  - 8. 1918, Dec. 31,J.W. Cunliffe to N.F. on the Ph.D., T.L.S.
  - 9. 1919, Feb. 15,Byron J. Rees to N.F. on the Ph.D., T.L.S.
  - 10. 1919, Feb 21,C.L. Maxey to N.F. on the Ph.D., T.L.S.
  - 11. 1919, Feb. 28,E.P. Dargan to N.F. on the Ph.D., A.L.S.
  - 12. 1919, Mar 1,W.B. Cairns to N.F. on the Ph.D., T.L.S.
  - 13. 1919, April 5,John M. Manly to N.F. on the Ph.D., T.L.S.
    N.F.'s note: typical of the leadership of the time, I agree, but...
  - 14. 1919, April 19,G.R. Elliot to N.F., criticisim of N.F.'s concept of humanism as reasoned but superficial., T.L.S.
  - 15. 1919, May 17,G.R. Elliott to N.F., completeness and control., T.L.S.
- CORRESPONDENCE (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1. 1928, Sept. 22,N.F. to P.H. Frye, invitation to write in humanistic manifesto ( Humanism and America)., T.L.
  - 2. 1928, Oct. 6,P.H. Frye to N.F., prevented from contributing by health., A.L.S.
  - 3. 1929, Jan. 4,N. F. to L.A.J. Mercier, needs date of article., T.L.
  - 4. 1929, Jan. 5,L.A.J. Mercier to N.F., On the symposium., A.L.S.
  - 5. 1929, Jan. 15,N.F. to L.A.J. Mercier, on the symposium., T.L.
  - 6. 1929, Jan. 29,N.F. to P.H. Frye, states that Frye need not commit himself., T.L.
  - 7. 1929, Feb. 4,P.H. Frye, to N.F., will attempt contribution., A.L.S.
  - 8. 1929, Feb. 11,L.A.J. Mercier to N.F., on the symposium's bibliography., A.L.S.
  - 9. 1929, Feb 12,N.F. to P.H. Frye, agrees on suggested subject--education., T.L.
  - 10. 1929, March 23,N.F. to L.A.J. Mercier., T.L.
  - 11. 1929, March 25,L.A.J. Mercier to N.F., on humanism and religion., A.L.S.
  - 12. 1929, Aug. 17,P.H. Frye, essay not ready., A.L.S.
  - 13. 1929, Aug. 23,N.F. to P.H. Frye, still hopeful., T.L.
  - 14. 1929, Aug. 30,N.F. to P.H. Frye, extends deadline., T.L.
  - 15. 1929, Sept. 7,P.H. Frye to N.F. on his progress., A.L.S.
  - 16. 1929, Oct. 26,N.F. to P.H. Frye, last chance, T.L.
  - 17. 1929, Oct 31,N.F. to P.H. Frye, possible divergence in views., T.L.
  - 18. 1929, Nov. 7,P.H. Frye to N.F., essay remains half-done., A.L.S.
  - 19. 1929, Dec 2,N.F. to P.H. Frye, suggests putting sophist essay in Forum or Bookman when completed., T.L.
- CORRESPONDENCE (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1. 1930, Jan. 5,Austin Warren to N.F., relays Babbitt's criticism., A.L.S.
  - 2. 1930, Jan. 15,Henry S. Canby to N.F., seeking a position., T.L.S.
  - 3. 1930, Jan 23,Odell Shepard to N.F., comment on speeches before the M.L.A., T.L.S.
  - 4. 1930, Feb. 22,Austin Warren to N.F., on Humanism and America, which had been published., A.L.S.
  - 5. 1930, March 3,N.F. to Austin Warren., T.L.
  - 6. 1930, March 5,Austin Warren to N.F., hopeless to save M.L.A. for humanism., A.L.S.
  - 7. 1930, March 7,the undersigned--32 in number--to the Literary Editor, group of antihumanists asking for mention of a single contemporary work of art produced or approved by an American Humanist., T.L.
  - 8. 1930, March 28,Harry H. Clark to N.F., suggestions for head of N.F.'s department., T.L.S.
  - 9. 1930, March 30,Nowell Smith (Oxford U.) to N.F. asks about Bernard Bandler., A.L.S.
  - 10. 1930, April 22,Austin Warren to W.F., wants advice., A.L.S.
  - 11. 1930, April 28,Austin Warren to N.F., congratulations on appointment as director of Iowa's School of Letters., A.L.S.
  - 12. 1930, May 3,Nowell Smith to N.F., advocates peaceful pursuasion., A.L.S.
  - 13. 1930, May 3,N.F. to Odell Shepard, congratulations on essay in Bookman., T.L.
  - 14. 1930, June 9,N.F. to L.A.J. Mercier, congratulations on essay in COMMONWEAL., T.L.
  - 15. 1930, June 11,L.A.J. Mercier to N.F., returns thanks., A.L.S.
  - 16. 1930, June 12,Austin Warren to N.F., has been taken in by the Bookman., A.L.S.
  - 17. 1930, June 16,N.F. to Austin Warren., T.L.
  - 18. 1930, June 17,N.F. to Odell Shepard, on [UNK] the M.L.A., T.L.
  - 19. 1930, June 18,Austin Warren to N.F.., A.L.S.
  - 20. 1930, Oct 16,Odell Shepard to N.F., appointment in M.L.A., T.L.S.
  - 21. 1930,election day, T.L., N.F. to Odell Shepard, renews offer for Shepard to teach at Chapel Hill.
  - 22. 1930., Nov. 8,W.T. Couch to Hazlitt, [UNK] about The Nation' s policy towards humanism, especially with reference to review of N.F.'s Toward Standards., T.L.
  - 23. 1930, Nov. 8,W.T. Couch to N.F. about letter to Hazlitt which had been enclosed, A.L.S.; (item 22 in this folder).
  - 24. 1930, Nov. 9,Odell Shepard to NF, a no to summer teaching., A.L.S.
  - 25. 1930, Nov. 10,Henry Hazlett to W.T. Couch useless to talk about what level an action is on--natural, human, etc., T.L.
  - 26. 1930, Nov. 13,W.T. Couch to Hazlitt, man being above nature simply means he can control it to some extent; humanitarianism is nonsense without free will; John Stuart Mills ideas on the natural., T.L.
  - 27. 1930, Nov. 13,W.T. Couch to NF, on controversy with Hazlitt., T.L.S.
  - 28. 1931, Jan. 11,NF to T.L. Couch, comments on Hazlitt versus Couch letters, T.L.; (items 22, 25 & 26).
  - 29. 1931, April 1,Bush to NF, Middle Ages based on unhumanistic doctrine of excess; no room in humanism for the whole of humanity., T.L.S.
  - 30. 1931, April 12,NF to Bush, [UNK] including everything mean nothing., T.L.
- CORRESPONDENCE (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1. 1934, Feb. 26,B. (?) Christian Richard to NF, includes clipping., A.L.S.
  - 2. 1938, Feb. 17,Theodore Spencer to NF on Ph.D programs at Harvard, includes reprint., A.L.S.
  - 3. 1940, Oct. 4,Merrits Y. Hughes to NF., T.L.S.
  - 4. 1940, Nov. 7,Percy W. Long to NF on M.L.A., T.L.S.
  - 5. 1941, Sept. 14,Dora D. Babbitt to NF, concerning Irving Babbitt., A.L.S.
  - 6. 1941, Nov. 18,Dora D. Babbitt to NF, criticism of NF's biographical sketch of Irving Babbitt., A.L.S.
  - 7. 1941, Nov. 23,Dora D. Babbitt to NF, same as above., A.L.S.
  - 8. 1944, March 15,Abraham Flexner to NF., T.L.S.
  - 9. 1945, June 28,George B. Abbe to NF, tells of book (his) on and against anti-Semitism., A.L.S.
  - 10. 1948, Jan, 3,Jay B. Hubbell to NF, about some meeting (in Detroit?)., T.L.S.
  - 11. 1948, April 4,Lionel Trilling (?)., A.L.S.
  - 12. 1951, Aug. 5,G.R. Elliot to NF, the weather and criticism of his humanism is now considered old-fashioned., T.LS.
  - 13. 1954, Jan. 6,Glenn S. Weight to NF, wants climmings, encloses copy of letter (NF to Weight) dated about March 27, 1947,which comments on post-W.W. II trends., T.L.S.
  - 14. 1966, Aug. 11,NF to Charles H. Foster on the past (some documents concerning humanis, A.L.S.
  - Correspondence between NF and the following: Gorha B. Munson (of Doubleday, Doran & Co.), John Farrar and Stanley W. Rinehart (of Farrar and Rinehart). (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Correspondence begins with T.L.S., Nov. 25, 1928, from Munston to NF, ends with T.L., May 22, 1930, from NF to Rinehart. Also includes:
    - 1. 1929, Jan. 21,Memorandum of agreement with Doubleday, Doran and Co., Ibc.
    - 2. Report on the new Rinehart and Farrar publishing house.
    - 3. 1929, Dec. 9,T.L. from NF to Farrar, G.R. Elliot to Robert Shafer about the Spring articl
    - 4. 1930, April 5,Robert Shafer to NF, suggestion on how profits from Humanism and America should be divided., T.L.S.
- NOTES, CLIPS, REPRINTS
  - Notes, clippings and reprints 1907-1918.This selection from early humanist literature includes articles by Irving Babbitt, Frank Mather and Paul E. More which appeared in the Nation, The Sewannee Review, and The English Journal. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Notes, clippings and reprints 1919-20,articles from a considerable no. of different publications (many by Babbitt). Emphatic criticism of Romanticis: Notes from the Psychology of Social Reconstruction by G.T.W. Patrick. Information on Ph.D. requirements. Essay by NF, A New Humanism. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Notes, clippings and reprints (1921-26).Articles from the Saturday Review of Literature, The New York Times Book Review and a variety of others all with some connection (perhaps indirectly) to humanism. No articles by NF possible except one, a typed essay whose authorship is not given. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Notes, clippings, and reprints 1928.Includes several book reviews of Munson's Destinations and More's The Demon of the Absolute. Numerous articles pertaining to humanism--including one by Babbitt and More's, Modern Currents in American Literature, with typed comment (probably NF's). (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Notes, clippings and reprints, Feb.-Dec., 1929.Articles and clippings pertaining to humanism. The variagation of the array of literary magazines shows great influence in this year. The Forum, The Saturday Review, The New York Times Book Review The Hound and Horn, America, Commonwealth, The Foxboro Reporter, The Carolina Magazine, Harper's, The Bookman, Creative Reading, The World, and several newspapers are represented. This folder is basically a collection of short items which are pro-humanist. Also included is the program of the 46th meeting of the M.L.A. A few short items (appearing in the publications) are authored by NF. For example, the article of Oct., 1929, about Dr. Charles Francis Potter concerning New Religion. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clippings and reprints, Jan.-March 1930.Short items about humanism supplied by news clipping service (located at 96 Warren St., New York City) and generally taken from newspapers. More controversial items (pro or anti-humanist) are here selected by NF from literary magazines. No author or publication dominates this selection. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Clippings and reprints April-June 1930.Articles by C. Hartley Grattan, Upton Sinclair, Alan Reynolds Thompson, and Allen Tate; some clippings and reprints from Saturday Review, New Republic, Virginia Quarterly--articles treat Humanism. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Clippings and articles May-Dec. 1930.This folder's contents are on the general subject of Humanism and personalities involved in the Movement. Articles from: Saturday Review of Literature, The Sewanee Review, The Pittsburch Press, The Harvard Advocate, and Harper's. Articles By: Percy H. Houston, H.S. Canby Rebecca West, Irving Babbit, and Linton F. Keith. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- REVIEWS
  - Reviews of Humanism and America by 1930clippings and articles--sources: Saturday Review, New York Herald-Tribune, Boston Evening Transcript, L.A. Times, DeMoines Sunday Register, Sewanee Review (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Articles, 1930,Principally on Irving Babbitt and Paul Elmer More: Saturday Review (Walter Lippmann); The New Freeman; Sewanee Review (Percy H. Houston). (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Reviews 1930-1(Articles and reprints) of Humanism in America edited by NF. The Folder contains chiefly commentary on the book from the clerical point of view--writings of Babbitt, More and G.R. Elliot considered most extensively: Articles from the Commonweal; America; Catholic News; and The Notre Dame Scholastic. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Reviews of The Critique of Humanism, Ed. by C. Hartley Grattan--most reviews make mention of NF and his relation to Humanism. Includes clippings from: N.Y. Times, Sewanee Review, The Hound and Horn; included also is book jacket from same. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Misc. clippings re: Humanism, most of which mention NF's name in relation to same. Also includes clipping of letter to editor of the Saturday Review from NF. discussing absolute and relative truth and misquotations by this magazine; also several clippings concerning I Babbit's typed copy of pp. 464-77 of The Nineteenth Century-- Oct. 1931by P.S. Richards. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Articles, 1932,specifically relating to Irving Babbit and Humanism in general: Sewanee Journal (C.H. Grattan); Hibbert Journal (Louis T. More) Review by Paul E. More; Article in Saturday Review by Irving Babbit--also Nov., 1932, copy of the Modern Schoolman containing 8 articles pertinent to Humanism; plus: 2 later articles--Dec., 1933 and Mar., 1934, from Fleur de Lis written about Babbit after his death. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Humanism in American Criticism, a bibliography by Arthur Berthold 1932: includes introductory quotations by NF and Irving; table of contents bibliographical listing of 42 works related to Humanism. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Clippings and Journals dealing primarily with Irving Babbit 1933-1961--includes writings by L.H. Hough; A.R. Caponigri; L.J.A. Mercer; S.E. Dubbel; A. Warren R. Bloom; R. Kirk; F.O. Matthiessen. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Misc. pieces 1905--Feb. 1930,RE: NF and Humanism: Convocation Ode H.M. J nes 1915; copy of January edition of the Bookman, Henry Hazlitt; NF's inaugural address, Iowa, 1930; NF's lecture notes on Irving Babbit's course on Romanticism in England, France and Germany. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Misc. pieces Mar. 1930--Nov. 4, 1933,RE: NF and Humanism: Mar. 1930, edition of the Bookman Irwin Edman; copy of Daily Tar Heal with article by NF--March 27, 1932; typed MS. titled Congres de Nimes, Paris, 1932, in French. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Misc. pieces, Jan., 1934--Oct., 1942,RE: NF and Humanism: Quotes from The Issue in the Higher Learning, Robert Maynard Hutchins--4 pages typed; Howard M. Jones; Rockform College Bulletin, Jan, 1936; S. Buchanan; Reprint of Toward an American Tradition by S.G. Brown; typed MS (1930's) The Teaching of the Native Language and Literature of France, by R. Brugere--In French and English; Sewanee Review; Hoxie Nealis Fairchild; April 12, 1942 article on Alfred Noyes, N.Y. Times book review E.K. Brown; Page of Handwritten Notes, NF's (?) about literary criticism, Oct. 21, 1942. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Misc. pieces, May, 1943--Nov, 1947,RE: NF and Humanism: Lynn T. White; Pico della Mirandola; several book reivews; Rene Wellek; James B. Conant; copy of The News Letter,Nov., 1947,; copy of The Journal of General Education. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Misc. pieces, July 1948--1966,RE: NF and Humanism: Robert M. Hutchins; W.T. Stage; Lawrence Bridges, Dec. 31, 1948; J.B. Rhine; Ledwig Lewisohn; Book reivews; the CEA critic RE: Babbit; Great Books; Convention Program; Times Literary Supplement RE: Julian Huxley and scientific humanism; Notes on Frost and Willa Cather and Foerster's life; other notes 1966, in NF' s hand RE: Babbit and More; Typed copy of reading list for English 189, 1966. (Box 3, Folder 6)
- CORRESPONDENCE MISC.
  - Folders 1,2,3, Letters from various American scholars commenting on the preface by Norman Foerster to Literary Scholarship: Its Functions and Prospects, compiled by several members of the University of Iowa faculty. Letters are listed alphabetically by sender.
    - a. From Gilbert W. Aron, 12 Oct., 1940. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - b. From G. Chinard, MS returned with letter-- 13 Oct., 1940.
    - c. From George Coffman, 10 Oct. 1940.
    - d. From R.S. Crane, no date.MS returned with letter.
    - e. From N.W. Dewittt, 7 Oct., 1940.
    - a. From R.C. Flickinger, 14 Oct., 1940. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - b. From (?) Funker--no letter, MS only--with comments in margin.
    - c. From Percy W. Long; no letter, MS only--with comments in margin and on last page.
    - d. From G.A. Harper, no letter, MS only--with comments in margin and on last page.
    - e. From E. Joliat, 14 Oct., 1940.
    - f. From Robert K. Root, 9 Oct., 1940.
    - a. From George Sherburn, 4 Oct., 1940,Ms returned with comments. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - b. From Horatio Smith, 9 Oct., 1940,MS returned.
    - c. From J.S.P. Tatlock, 5 Oct., 1940,MS returned with comments in pencil.
    - d. From K. Young, 11 Oct., 1940,MS returned with comments.
    - e. From John G. Walz, 16 Oct., 1940.
    - f. From Curt Zimansky (?), no date.
    - g. From J.H., no date,penciled in longhand.
  - Fragments; undated pieces; notes and personal items, lists of outgoing (?) correspondence of NF to Aswell, Elliott (incoming) Shafer, Huston, Munson, Collins Knickerbocker, Mather, T.S. Eliot, Spring, More, Bandler, Gass Thompson, Clark, Shepard, Wanan, Gair, Merirer. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Fragments, undated pieces Theater as Religion, article by Maxwell Anderson; undated letter from Christopher Hollis written examination for Enclish Ph.D; Religious Perspectives of College Teaching, by Hoxie Fairchild; Archibald Macleish; Cards with notes on old Aristotle; The Unity of Europe, by F.M. Eachran; notes on view of scholarship; notes on Babbit. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Correspondence: (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Irving Babbitt to NF 22 Aug 1911; 1 Apr 1912; 25 Aug 1919; 16 Nov 1919; 30 Jul 1924; 8 Mar 1925; 12 Apr 1926; 7 Jul 1929; 16 Jun 1930; 15 Jun 1932), (10 letters
  - Paul E. More to NF 22 May 1913; 26 June 1913; 3 Jul 1913; 25 Jan 1921; 9 Aug 1922; 27 Feb 1924; 1 Dec 1925; 11 Jul 1933; 18 Nov 1933), (10 Letters:
  - Dora Babbitt to NF 9 May 1933; 13 Jul 1933; 5 Dec 1941; 5 Jan 1942), (4 letters:
  - Telegram from Esther Babbitt Howe to NF, 15 Jul 1933.
  - Babbitt and More to Foerster
    - #plea for unity among young men of the movement Aug 25, 1919,Irving Babbitt.
    - #Paul E. More, June 26, 1913,comments on Foerster's article for the Nation, I feel the review should be more psychological--less literary.
    - #Irving Babbitt, June 16,1930, Things are looking pretty black for humanists.
    - #Irving Babbitt, July 30, 1924,Foerster's Nature in American Literature had good reviews but none say anything about author's humanistic thesis.
      5-3 TS to NF 12 June 1929 missing 9/74
- Correspondence: (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Paul E. More to NF 21 Jun 1928; 7 Dec 1928; 23 Jan 1929; 4 Feb 1929; 28 Feb 1929; 8 Mar 1929; 11 May 1929; 5 Jul 1929; 6 Sep 1929; 12 Oct 1929; 17 Oct 1929), (11 letters:
  - NF to Paul E. More 16 Jan 1929; 15 Feb 1929; 25 Feb 1929; 6 Mar 1929; 9 May 1929; 30 Aug 1929;telegram N.D.; 17 Oct 1929., (8 letters:
  - Short biography of I.B.: Written by Irving Babbitt in response to questions put by Norman Foerster. Received by N.F. August 28, 1929.
  - Correspondence: NF to Dora Babbitt 8 May 1943; 18 Aug 1943), (2 letters:
  - Dora Babbitt to NF 18 May 1943), (1 letter:
    - #NF to Mrs. Dora Babbitt, Aug 18, 1943;speaks of publishing the Babbitt--More letters.
    - #Paul E. More to NF, Feb 4, 1929.
      More convinced than ever that omission of the old humanist is best thing for the manifesto.
    - #More to NF, March 8, 1929.
    - #NF's work on the book, it is like driving pigs to market.
    - #More to NF, July 5, 1929.
      Even with Babbitt in, he wants out.
    - #More to NF, Jan 23, 1929.
      If Babbitt and Mather go in, he will.
    - #Received by NF Aug 28, 1929--
      a four page autobiography of Babbitt written in response to questions put forward by NF. Special emphasis on development of humanistic conviction (who and what influenced). Does not like being called new humanist. Humanism: very old way of looking at life.
- Correspondence: (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - T.S. Eliot to NF 5 [UNK] 1928; 14 Aug 1928; 18 Feb 1929; 22 April 1929; 29 April 1929; 13 Aug 1929; 14 April 1930), (7 letters:
    see [UNK] to Eliot
  - T.S. Eliot to Farrar & Rinehart ( n.d.)., 1 letter:
  - NF to T.S. Eliot ( 5 Feb 1929; 1 Mar 1929; 9 Apr 1929; 17 Apr 1929; 13 May 1929; 12 Jun 1929; 29 Aug 1929; 31 Aug 1929)., 8 letters:
  - Gorham B. Munson to Nf ( 4 Sep 1928; 16 Dec 1928; 25 Feb 1929; 16 Mar 1929; 6 Jul 1929; 16 Jul 1929; 31 Aug 1929; 4 Sept 1929; 19 Sept 1929; 1 Oct 1929; 28 Nov 1929; 3 Dec 1929; 24 May 1930; 5 Jul 1930; 14 Aug 1930), 15 letters:
  - NF to Gorham B. Munson ( 17 Aug 1928; 21 Sept 1928; 1 Mar 1929; 10 Sep 1929; 7 Oct 1929; 30 Nov 1929; 30 May 1930; 12 Aug 1930)., 8 letters:
  - F.J. Mather to NF ( 27 Oct 1926; 20 Jan 1929; 22 Jul 1929; 13 Sept. 1929; 22 Nov 1929; 29 Nov 1929; 21 Feb 1930)., 8 letters:
  - NF to F. J. Mather ( 16 Jan 1929; 16 Sep 1929; 30 Aug 1929)., 3 letters:
  - #T.S. Eliot to NF, April 22, 1929.
    Agrees that Grench and Germans should be kept out of NF's symposium on humanism--should keep issue limited to Babbitt's brand. Tells of fear of religious hierarchy which is not only civilized--may write on danger of religion without humanism.
  - #T.S. Eliot to NF, Aug 13, 1929.
    Refers to his own contribution to the symposium as a jumble of themes which ought to be analysed into a book.
  - #NF to T.S. Eliot, Aug 31, 1929.
    NF quotes G.R. Eliot, that G.R. agrees with about 51 percent of T.S. Eliot's essay but this is about average agreement expected among contributors.
  - #NF to Gorham B. Munson, Aug 17, 1928.
    Suggest Munson contribute to symposium--since he is nonacademic with pungent style--something as counter-irritant to Menckenism.
  - #NF to Munson, Nov 30, 1929.
    Refers to T.S. Eliot as greenish-blue (as opposed to true blue humanist) but says that his skit is harmless.
  - #Munson to NF, Sept 4, 1929.
    Munson sends Foerster his contribution--though may be too long (9,000 words) he had laid himself out to break the grip upon our literature of the popular romantic critics.
  - #Munson to NF, Dec 3, 1929.
    Suggestions for jacket and advertising. Must have dramatic appeal.
  - #Munson to NF, May 24, 1930.Controversy over Humanism and America has made him lose all respect for the opposition.
  - #Munson to NF, Aug 14, 1930.Speaks of his book to be published in September.
  - #F.J. Mather to NF, Jan 20, 1929.If BAbbitt contributes, so will Mather and More.
  - #F.J. Mather to NF, Nov 22, 1929.Finds it necessary to add extra paragraph to contribution, to make it clear the implications of view that the modernistic aesthetic has permanency.
- Correspondence: (Box 5, Folder 4)